Guide to the Emil Schwarzhaupt Foundation Papers 1945-1987
University of Chicago Library
- Series II: Application for Funds and Grants
  - South Chicago Community Center, Pamphlets, news clippings, and notes by Carl Tjerandsen about the Trumbull Park project (Box 40, Folder 11)
  - Springfield College, Community Tensions Center, Applications and recommendations, 1956-1957 (Box 40, Folder 12)
  - Springfield College, Community Tensions Center, Correspondence, 1956-1959 (Box 40, Folder 13)
  - Springfield College, Community Tensions Center, Correspondence, 1960-1963 (Box 40, Folder 14)
  - Springfield College, Community Tensions Center, Progress and annual reports, 1957-1960 (Box 41, Folder 1)
  - Springfield College, Community Tensions Center, Hans B. C. Spiegel, "Intergroup Tensions and the Campus," October 1962 (Box 41, Folder 2)
  - Springfield College, Community Tensions Center, Pamphlets and article reprints (Box 41, Folder 3)
  - Tufts University, Civic Education Center, Applications and recommendations, 1954-1956 (Box 41, Folder 4)
  - Tufts University, Civic Education Center, Correspondence, 1950-1953 (Box 41, Folder 5)
  - Tufts University, Civic Education Center, Correspondence, 1954 (Box 41, Folder 6)
  - Tufts University, Civic Education Center, Correspondence, 1955 (Box 41, Folder 7)
  - Tufts University, Civic Education Center, Correspondence, 1956-1963 (Box 41, Folder 8)
  - Tufts University, Civic Education Center, Distribution report and analyses of Civic Education Project, 1954, 1957-1959 (Box 41, Folder 9)
  - Tufts University, Civic Education Center, Pamphlets of the Civic Education Project (Box 41, Folder 10-12)
  - Tufts University, Civic Education Center, Pamphlets of the Civic Education Project (Box 42, Folder 1-6)
  - Tufts University, Civic Education Center, Typescript drafts of two pamphlets (Box 42, Folder 7)
  - Tufts University, Civic Education Center, Progress report on pamphlet compilation, 1950, and suggested activities (Box 43, Folder 1)
  - Tufts University, Civic Education Center, Pamphlets, news clippings, and article reprints (Box 43, Folder 2)
  - Unitarian Service Committee, Citizen Education Program, Applications and recommendations, 1955; progress reports, July-August 1956 (Box 43, Folder 3)
  - Unitarian Service Committee, Citizen Education Program, Correspondence, September 1955-1956 (Box 43, Folder 4)
  - Unitarian Service Committee, Citizen Education Program, Correspondence, June 1956-November 1966 (Box 43, Folder 5)
  - Unitarian Service Committee, Citizen Education Program, Mrs. Dudley Moore, "Report to the Schwarzhaupt Foundation on the Citizenship Education Program, Gallup Indian Community Center; Section I, Philosophy and Background," July 1965 (Box 43, Folder 6)
  - Unitarian Service Committee, Citizen Education Program, Mrs. Dudley Moore, "Report to the Schwarzhaupt Foundation on the Citizenship Education Program, Gallup Indian Community Center. "Section II, Implementation" November 1966 (Box 43, Folder 7)
  - Unitarian Service Committee, Citizen Education Program, Pamphlets and news clippings (Box 43, Folder 8)
  - United Community Fund of San Francisco, Applications and recommendations, 1957-1960 (Box 43, Folder 9)
  - United Community Fund of San Francisco, Correspondence, 1957-1958 (Box 43, Folder 10)
  - United Community Fund of San Francisco, Correspondence, 1959-1962 (Box 43, Folder 11)
  - United Community Fund of San Francisco, "Progress Report, Neighborhood Council, May 1, 1958 to May 1, 1959" (Box 43, Folder 12)
  - United Community Fund of San Francisco, "Second Year Progress Report of Neighborhood Councils in San Francisco, May 1, 1959 to April 30, 1960" (Box 43, Folder 13)
  - United Community Fund of San Francisco, News clippings and notes by Carl Tjerandsen; newsletter, Upper Noe Valley Neighborhood Bulletin Board, 1959-1960 (Box 43, Folder 14)
  - University of California, Cowell Extramural Education Program, Applications and recommendations, correspondence, and newsletter, 1971-1972 (related to visit of Septima Clark) (Box 44, Folder 1)
  - University of Chicago (soliciting funds), Correspondence, and pamphlets, 1945-1959 (Box 44, Folder 2)
  - University of Chicago, American Indian Chicago Conference, Applications and recommendations, 1960-1961; correspondence, 1960-1963 (Box 44, Folder 3)
  - University of Chicago, American Indian Chicago Conference, Reports, 1960-1961 (Box 44, Folder 4)
  - University of Chicago, American Indian Chicago Conference, Newsletters, Indian Voices, 1963-1965 (Box 44, Folder 5)
  - University of Chicago, American Indian Chicago Conference, "A Program for Indian Citizens; A Summary Report," January 1961; "Declaration of Indian Purpose," June 13-20, 1961; Murray Wax, "American Indian Education as a Cross-Cultural Transaction" (Box 44, Folder 6)
  - University of Chicago, American Indian Chicago Conference, Pamphlets and news clippings (Box 44, Folder 7-8)
  - University of Chicago, Committee on Education for American Citizenship, Application, October 22, 1951; "First Quarterly Report to the Schwarzhaupt Foundation," April 1, 1952; summary of activities of the Committee, May 15, 1952 (Box 44, Folder 9)
  - University of Chicago, Committee on Education for American Citizenship, Correspondence, October 1950-April 1952 (Box 44, Folder 10)
  - University of Chicago, Committee on Education for American Citizenship, Correspondence, May 1952-June 1953 (Box 44, Folder 11)
  - University of Chicago, Committee on Education for American Citizenship, Minutes of the Committee, January-June 1952 (Box 44, Folder 12)
  - University of Chicago, Committee on Education for American Citizenship, Notes and proposals on possible projects; news clippings (Box 44, Folder 13)
  - University of Chicago, Committee on Education for American Citizenship, Drafts of preliminary recommendations to the Schwarzhaupt Foundation (Box 44, Folder 14)
  - University of Chicago, Committee on Education for American Citizenship, "The Problem of Education for Citizenship," 1953 (Box 45, Folder 1)
  - University of Chicago, Civic Education Directory Project, Correspondence, April-September 1953 (Box 45, Folder 2)
  - University of Chicago, Civic Education Directory Project, Correspondence, October 1953-September 1955 (Box 45, Folder 3)
  - University of Chicago, Civic Education Directory Project, Correspondence, January 1956-April 1957 (Box 45, Folder 4)
  - University of Chicago, Civic Education Directory Project, Correspondence, May-June 1957 (Box 45, Folder 5)
  - University of Chicago, Civic Education Directory Project, Correspondence, July-October 1957 (Box 45, Folder 6)
  - University of Chicago, Civic Education Directory Project, Correspondence, November 1957-May 1958 (Box 45, Folder 7)
  - University of Chicago, Civic Education Directory Project, Correspondence, June-December 1958 (Box 45, Folder 8)
  - University of Chicago, Civic Education Directory Project, Correspondence, 1959-1960 (Box 45, Folder 9)
  - University of Chicago, Civic Education Directory Project, Correspondence, 1961-1964 (Box 45, Folder 10)
  - University of Chicago, Civic Education Directory Project, Drafts and promotional literature for Civic Education Directory (Box 45, Folder 11)
  - University of Chicago, Civic Education Directory Project, Newsletters, mimeographed information sheets, and articles (Box 45, Folder 12)
  - University of Chicago, Fox Indians Project, Tama, Iowa, Applications and recommendations, 1954, 1957 (Box 45, Folder 13)
  - University of Chicago, Fox Indians Project, Tama, Iowa, Correspondence, 1954 (Box 45, Folder 14)
  - University of Chicago, Fox Indians Project, Tama, Iowa, Correspondence, 1955-1970 (Box 45, Folder 15)
  - University of Chicago, Fox Indians Project, Tama, Iowa, Reports, 1954-1956; Sol Tax, "Symposium; The Fox Project; A Program in Action Anthropology," March 4, 1957 (Box 46, Folder 1)
  - University of Chicago, Fox Indians Project, Tama, Iowa, Fred Gearing and Lisa Peattie, "A Documentary History of the Fox Project," 1955 (Box 46, Folder 2)
  - University of Chicago, Fox Indians Project, Tama, Iowa, Fred Gearing, Robert McC. Netting and Lisa R. Peattie, Documentary History of the Fox Project, 1948-1959; A Program in Action Anthropology (Chicago; University of Chicago Department of Anthropology, 1960) (Box 46, Folder 3)
  - University of Chicago, Fox Indians Project, Tama, Iowa, Sol Tax, "Values in Action; The Fox Project," December 28, 1957; "A Project in Behalf of the Mesquakies and Whites in Iowa," 1953; "The Mesquakies of Iowa," 1953 (Box 46, Folder 4)
  - University of Chicago, Fox Indians Project, Tama, Iowa, Proposals, reports, and news clippings (Box 46, Folder 5)
  - University of Chicago, Human Relations Center-Center for Community Leader Training, Applications and recommendations, 1954-1957 (Box 46, Folder 6)
  - University of Chicago, Human Relations Center-Center for Community Leader Training, Correspondence, June 1954-May 1955 (Box 46, Folder 7)
  - University of Chicago, Human Relations Center-Center for Community Leader Training, Correspondence, July 1955-June 1958 (Box 46, Folder 8)
  - University of Chicago, Human Relations Center-Center for Community Leader Training, "Summary of Activities September 1955 to May 1957"; Aimee Isgrig, "Developing Leadership For Community Improvement," March 1957; notes on projects by Carl Tjerandsen (Box 46, Folder 9)
  - University of Chicago, Human Relations Center-Center for Community Leader Training, Haimowitz, Morris L. and Aimee Isgrig, "Report of the Human Relations Center," September 1, 1957, Part I, "The Human Relation Center" (Box 47, Folder 1)
  - University of Chicago, Human Relations Center-Center for Community Leader Training, Haimowitz, Morris L. and Aimee Isgrig, "Report of the Human Relations Center," September 1, 1957, Part II, "Lay Leadership Training in Communities" (Box 47, Folder 2)
  - University of Chicago, Human Relations Center-Center for Community Leader Training, Haimowitz, Morris L. and Aimee Isgrig, "Report of the Human Relations Center," September 1, 1957, Part III, "Community Organization Training" (Box 47, Folder 3)
  - University of Chicago, Human Relations Center-Center for Community Leader Training, Haimowitz, Morris L. and Aimee Isgrig, "Report of the Human Relations Center," September 1, 1957, Part IV, "Summer Workshop" (Box 47, Folder 4)
  - University of Chicago, Human Relations Center-Center for Community Leader Training, Haimowitz, Morris L. and Aimee Isgrig, "Report of the Human Relations Center," September 1, 1957, Part V, "Seminars on Community Problems" (Box 47, Folder 5)
  - University of Chicago, Human Relations Center-Center for Community Leader Training, Haimowitz, Morris L. and Aimee Isgrig, "Report of the Human Relations Center," September 1, 1957, Part VI, "Education 322" (Box 47, Folder 6)
  - University of Chicago, Human Relations Center-Center for Community Leader Training, "Sixth Annual Workshop in Community Human Relations," 1957 (Box 47, Folder 7)
  - University of Chicago, Human Relations Center-Center for Community Leader Training, News clippings (Box 47, Folder 8)
  - University of Chicago, Research Projects, Roy Ingram, Applications and recommendations, 1957; correspondence, 1958; preliminary report, 1958 (Box 48, Folder 1)
  - University of Chicago, Research Projects, Leonard Gardner, Applications and recommendations, 1955, 1957; correspondence, April 27, 1955-December 12, 1958 (Box 48, Folder 2)
  - University of Chicago, Research Projects, Leonard Gardner, Applications and recommendations, 1955, 1957, "Citizenship Education; Practice and Theory," The School Review (January 1956); 29-35; "Not Knowledge, But Action" Phi Delta Kappan 37 (December 1955); 99-104; "The Role of the Expert in Policy Formation; The Problem of Education For Citizenship," December 1953 (Box 48, Folder 3)
  - University of Chicago, Research Projects, Robert Horwitz, applications and recommendations, 1953 (Box 48, Folder 4)
  - University of Chicago, Research Projects, Robert Horwitz, applications and recommendations, Correspondence, 1953 (Box 48, Folder 5)
  - University of Chicago, Research Projects, Robert Horwitz, applications and recommendations, 1954 (Box 48, Folder 6)
  - University of Chicago, Research Projects, Robert Horwitz, applications and recommendations, 1965 (Box 48, Folder 7)
  - University of Chicago, Research Projects, Robert Horwitz, applications and recommendations, "Civic Education Bibliography; Outline of Contents," n.d.; article reprint (Box 48, Folder 8)
  - University of Chicago, Research Projects, Robert Horwitz, applications and recommendations, "The Political Philosophy of Civic Education, Parts I & II," 1954 (Box 48, Folder 9)
  - University of Chicago, Research Projects, Robert Horwitz, applications and recommendations, "John Dewey," 1961; "John Dewey's Political Hypothesis and Citizenship Education," 1961 (Box 48, Folder 10)
  - University of Chicago, Southwest Citizenship Education Program, Application, 1958 (Box 48, Folder 11)
  - University of Miami, Applications and recommendations, 1952, 1953, 1959, 1961; summary report, 1947 (Box 49, Folder 1-3)
  - University of Miami, Correspondence, 1945-1948 (Box 49, Folder 4)
  - University of Miami, Correspondence, 1949-1959 (Box 49, Folder 5)
  - University of Miami, Correspondence, 1961-1979 (Box 49, Folder 6)
  - University of Miami, Pamphlets and news clippings (Box 49, Folder 7)
  - University of Michigan, Survey Research Center, Applications and recommendations, 1955-1958 (Box 49, Folder 8)
  - University of Michigan, Survey Research Center, Correspondence, 1955 (Box 49, Folder 9)
  - University of Michigan, Survey Research Center, Correspondence, 1956 (Box 49, Folder 10)
  - University of Michigan, Survey Research Center, Correspondence, 1957-1958 (Box 49, Folder 11)
  - University of Michigan, Survey Research Center, Correspondence, 1959-1968 (Box 49, Folder 12)
  - University of Michigan, Survey Research Center, Robert Weiss, Carol Slater, and Dora Cafagna, A Study of the League of Women Voters of the United States, Report I. The League Member Talks about the League (Ann Arbor; University of Michigan Survey Research Center, October 1956) (Box 49, Folder 13)
  - University of Michigan, Survey Research Center, Robert Weiss, Carol Slater, and Dora Cafagna, A Study of the League of Women Voters of the United States, Report II. Community Attitudes Toward the League (Ann Arbor; University of Michigan Survey Research Center, February 1957) (Box 49, Folder 14)
  - University of Michigan, Survey Research Center, Robert Weiss, Carol Slater, and Dora Cafagna, A Study of the League of Women Voters of the United States, Report III. Some Problems of League Membership; Cross-Sectional Membership and Member Activity, August 1957 (Box 50, Folder 1)
  - University of Michigan, Survey Research Center, Robert Weiss, Carol Slater, and Dora Cafagna, A Study of the League of Women Voters of the United States, Report IV. Organizational Phase, Part 1; Factors in League Functioning, August 1957) (Box 50, Folder 2)
  - University of Michigan, Survey Research Center, Robert Weiss, Carol Slater, and Dora Cafagna, A Study of the League of Women Voters of the United States, Report V. Organizational Phase, Part 2; Factors in League Effectiveness, April 1958) (Box 50, Folder 3)
  - University of Michigan, Survey Research Center, Questionnaire materials (Box 50, Folder 4)
  - University of Michigan, Survey Research Center, Bibliographies (Box 50, Folder 5)
  - University of Michigan, Survey Research Center, Pamphlets and news clippings (Box 50, Folder 6)
  - University of Washington, Bureau of Community Development, Application, correspondence, pamphlet, news clipping, 1957 (Box 50, Folder 7)
  - Welfare Council of Metropolitan Chicago, Applications and recommendations, 1956-1957 (Box 50, Folder 8)
  - Welfare Council of Metropolitan Chicago, Correspondence, February-July 1956 (Box 50, Folder 9)
  - Welfare Council of Metropolitan Chicago, Correspondence, September 1956-June 1957 (Box 50, Folder 10)
  - Welfare Council of Metropolitan Chicago, Correspondence, November 1957-October 1961 (Box 50, Folder 11)
  - Welfare Council of Metropolitan Chicago, Reports, 1960-1961; notes by Carl Tjerandsen (Box 50, Folder 12)
  - Welfare Council of Metropolitan Chicago, Memorandums and minutes, 1957 (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - Welfare Council of Metropolitan Chicago, Newsletter, Building Chicago, 1959-1961 (Box 51, Folder 2)
  - Welfare Council of Metropolitan Chicago, Pamphlets and news clippings (Box 51, Folder 3)
  - Welfare Council of Metropolitan Chicago, "First Annual Report of the Citizen Participation Project" (Box 51, Folder 4)
  - West Central Organization, Detroit, Applications and recommendations, correspondence, news clippings, 1965-1966 (Box 51, Folder 5)
  - Young Women's Christian Association, Mississippi District, Applications and recommendations, reports, pamphlets, 1958, 1960, 1962 (Box 51, Folder 6)
  - Young Women's Christian Association, Mississippi District, Correspondence, 1958-1963 (Box 51, Folder 7)
- Series III: Photographs
  - Subseries 1: Highlander Folk School
    - Photographs by Emil Willimetz, 1-"Etowah County, Alabama road sign" 2-"Leading Sacred Harp Singing" [Etowah County] 3-"Dirt road leading up Sand Mountain to Bluff Road community" [Etowah County] 4-"Mr. and Mrs. J. J. Brand of the Bluff Road community with a quilt she had just finished" [Etowah County] 5-"Bass Morton-Chairman of the Altoona Co-op Board" [Etowah County] 6-"Building Feed Mill addition to the Altoona Co-op" [Etowah County] 7-"State maintained ferry crossing Coosa river. This is the shortest point between Hokes Bluff community and the Coatsbend community" [Etowah County] 8-"Hokes Bluff Farmers Union Co-op" [Etowah County] 9-"Coatsbend F. U. Co-op" [Etowah County] (Box 52, Folder 1)
    - Photographs by Ida Berman, 1-"Learning to Pronounce Words Used in Literacy Tests, John's Island" 2-"Presbyterian Community Center, Wadmalaw Island; Literacy School held here" 3-"A Typical Home From Which Adult Students Come to Citizenship Schools" 4-"Illiterate Learning to Write on St. John's Island" 5-"St. John's Island Adult School" 6-"Charleston Heights Adult School" 7-"Edisto Island Adult School" 8-"Charleston Heights Adult School" 9-"Wadmalaw Island Adult School" 10-"Front Room in St. John's Island Adult School. Building is a COOP. The building was financed by Highlander" 11-"Reading Aloud, St. John's Island" (Box 52, Folder 2)
  - Subseries 2: Hyde Park-Kenwood Community Conference
    - #1-"Block organization clean-up drive" [4700 block of South Drexel, Chicago] #2-"Audience at Meeting" [Possibly in old YMCA building at 53rd and Dorchester, Chicago] #3-Boys picking up litter near 48th and Drexel, Chicago #4-"Block meeting" #5-"Blueprint for Action" [meeting around table] (Box 52, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 3: Migrant Ministry, National Council of the Churches of Christ in the USA
    - #6-Home of a farm laborer [ca. September 1956] #7-Boys with dog outside tar paper house [September 1956?] (Box 52, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 4: National Council of Catholic Churches
    - #8-Men posing for picture at conference in Lackawanna, New York [July 9, 1956] (Box 52, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 5: Penn Community Services, Inc.
    - #9-10-Voter registration workshops [January 11 and 12, 1963, St. Helena Island, South Carolina] (Box 52, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 6: Unitarian Service Committee, Gallup, New Mexico Citizenship Education Program
    - Educational slides with color drawings, also a sheet with the caption to each slide [used to teach voter registration], 38 University of Chicago, Special Collections Research Center Emil Schwarzhaupt Foundation. Papers 1 (Box 52, Folder 4)